[SPEAKER_01]: This is a question on practice for lay people.
[SPEAKER_01]: How should a lay person practice, if their goal is nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or at least some stage towards it, I presume.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can't attain nibbāna as a lay person.
[SPEAKER_01]: The suttas are pretty clear on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean you can't practice towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, well, you would practice in the same way the monks do, just on the basis of a greater compromise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Compromise of a household life.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the practice does not somehow miraculously become different, because you can't leave your home, or you can't leave your family, or you have a duty towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you can do a different thing towards the same goal of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still the same practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, often it can feel like a... like a high standard for a lay person to achieve.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like keeping the eight precepts, celibate, practice towards the right view, or maybe even non-return.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that's possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that was in the suttas recorded.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what also always those... what those suttas would always also say was quite clearly that in order for one to practice successfully, whether a monk or a layperson, he needs to understand the peril of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind needs to be free from hindrances on the basis of thorough virtue and sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, the difference basically was only... it wasn't in the path they were applying themselves to,
[SPEAKER_00]: The difference was simply in the circumstances they were keeping them back, but the practice was the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if it feels like a high, like a tall order, well, it's normal, it's going to feel that way, and it's fine to feel that way, but it's important to not then try to devalue or lower the threshold.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, because it just seems so unattainable, so give me something simpler.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: If actually the goal and the threshold remains high, even your failure to reach it will constitute more successful practice than successfully practicing towards a lower threshold, towards something that's not the beginning of the dhamma, but you were led to believe it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The good example of that is this, like, you know, it seems to be quite...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I don't know how prevalent, but... but I think there are probably quite a few people that, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: You kind of delusionally believe, you know, whether through their own doing or because they were led astray, that you can keep the five precepts and practice the dhamma as a layperson.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You look at any sutta, whenever the Buddha taught the five precepts, it was just to get better rebirths, heavenly rebirths, to enjoy sensuality further, instructing the spouses, you know, how to look after each other, how to be faithful, because they're going to get great sensual rewards.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was quite clearly not presented as the Noble Eightfold Path, you know, the one way only towards purification of being, the Satipaṭṭhāna and Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was clearly presented to those who don't want to practice, who are not interested in practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, okay, well, still, if you have a degree of virtue on the level of five precepts, a degree of honesty, a degree of reasoning, looking after your family...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, the Buddha was teaching people how to spend their money.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's something like it's quite delusional to believe that these things somehow also lead you to nibbāna, when the context in the suttas is quite clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, whenever there were lay people, quite, you know, the foremost, nāndamātā, the foremost in jhānas, a lay woman, all the other householders, they had many disciples, they were all fully established in virtue, eight precepts, so the parallels of sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensory strength, all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how they got where they were.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you also had lay people in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: There were sotāpānas, or sakadāgāmīs.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they were not... they were living by five precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that was after.
[SPEAKER_00]: After they got their right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they were lucky enough to talk to the Buddha and the Buddha to guide them step by step, then they went back home and were content with their attainment, and then kept the five precepts and remained being a good person.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they were clearly not practicing further.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when the Buddha did instruct, for example, Anantapindika, you know, the famous instruction, before he even started talking anything about the dhamma to him,
[SPEAKER_00]: He was... he first, obviously, the generosity, the merit that you make, elevated mind, talking about the heavens, the good rebirths, and then he was talking about the perils of sensuality, the absolute deprivation of sensual desires, the... the... the bait, the trap, the suffering, all of that, and then he said... then he... his mind was ready to hear the dhamma, and then he taught in dhamma, he got the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if today you were taught the dhamma, you're not getting the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because you're not seeing the depth of the perils of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it wasn't taught, generally, to lay people, the dhamma, for, who knows, half of half of the Buddha's life, probably.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite a few decades.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because it says in the sutras, we do not teach this.
[SPEAKER_00]: We do not teach this.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because they would leave.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, it's incompatible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, obviously, as I said, the people have all this access to the suttas and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Plus, let's not even get into, you know, the whole idea of you can practice meditation and meditation techniques that somehow lead you to the meat of the practice on the basis of your five precepts or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no such sutta at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even satipaṭṭhāna, as we said before, or ānāpānasati, was taught to noble disciples, or if they were just short of noble disciples, it was still taught to the monks, at least, who were fully ready for that, through sense restraint and virtue, in terms of the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this whole view that you can kind of be a householder,
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep the five precepts, you know, do your best in that regard, and do your meditation technique, and somehow that constitutes your practice for dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if monks who would have given up a lot more,
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to do all these other things in terms of the Buddha's instruction, you know, the detailed instruction, and repetitive, and constantly having to remind them, and a right sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_00]: They still need to do a lot on the basis of already having done a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: Giving up the household, the attachments, the bonds, all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they need to do a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you have somebody who hasn't even given all of that up, and needs to do even less.
[SPEAKER_00]: For the same practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's simply irrational, even if you think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Put aside that the suttas simply don't support that idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just stop and think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Surely, it would be other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: Surely, if somebody would not have given up the big part of obstruction for the goal of the holy life, would need to do then even a lot more, just to compensate for that compromise.
[SPEAKER_00]: And somebody who would have given it already up and lives already in a higher kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: In a higher environment of sensory strain, well, they would need... they would need to do less.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is, if you feel disheartened, oh, but it's just so much, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But don't obscure the fact that it is... that's the threshold.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you sort of calm down and come to terms with it, if you still keep trying towards that which feels too much, you are actually still getting closer to it, even through your failures.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, keep the five precepts, and then keep the eight precepts every now and then, but keep them really unconditionally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And don't look for meditation techniques to compensate for your intentionally chosen unsuitable environment, but take responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then feel the weight of that choice, feel the weight of the compromise.
[SPEAKER_00]: And through doing that,
[SPEAKER_00]: You are actually on the right track.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you never become a monk, you are still practicing more rightly than somebody who would have lowered the threshold just because the threshold they hear upsets them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It makes them feel bad, or it makes them feel disheartened, and they don't want to do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, the threshold remains the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I basically...
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is a peak of the mountain you have to climb to,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the peak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you don't aim in the direction of that peak, because it's too much, and start walking in the opposite direction, you're not getting closer to the peak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you climb other mountains, it's not the one you should be climbing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the point is to recognize that, yeah, it feels too high.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't even know I can do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, at least if I don't lower it down, just to please myself, my ignorant self, my aims will be aiming high where they should.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, when you aim high, even when you fail, you fail relatively higher than you were before.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same, same principle in education or in any other field.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you aim for, for like a
[SPEAKER_00]: Higher goal, or a more, kind of, accurate, sort of, higher purpose, even your failure will be a relative success.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if I lower the threshold and tell you, you know, just do this, well, you're going to aim even lower now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going to fall even lower than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like all this insistence on sensitivity and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not just to dishearten and, oh, this is just for the monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's for anybody who wants to practice the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is the beginning of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you read the suttas, you will arrive at the very same conclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to take my word for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even like, as I said, Nanda Mata that I mentioned, you know, she was like anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: And she, when she talked about herself, she said, and she had a husband, and she had a kid, before.
[SPEAKER_00]: But she said, even then, since she was a young girl, when she was given to her husband, you know, in marriage, she was never unfaithful to him, even in her thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let alone in the body of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize that she was already quite a developed human being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, how many people today can say that even mentally they don't transgress?
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't have a thought of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize she was dutiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: She bore him a kid.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he died, she immediately became celibate.
[SPEAKER_00]: She was simply not interested in any of that since way before.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when her own son was imprisoned, falsely imprisoned, falsely accused, killed, she didn't go and fight the king for injustice.
[SPEAKER_00]: She said her mind remained unchanged and then decided to put the praise there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, wow, you can purify thoughts in the manifestations.
[SPEAKER_00]: As they manifest, they're already clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, yeah, a lay person can do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even back then, that was impressive.
[SPEAKER_00]: There were monks who couldn't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, it's not about, oh, you must become a monk or a nun.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about, you mustn't lower the threshold, and then keep trying towards that level, and understand that even if you're failing, you're failing in regard to the right direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are actually going forward.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe not as fast as you would like to, or as others would promise you,
[SPEAKER_00]: But you are going forward.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through that repetition of failure of the right aim, you are climbing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, some people might say that, okay, well, I'm not so good with my virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: I keep five pieces every now and then, eight pieces every now and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: I fail at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, I compensate that with meditation technique, meditation whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, you have basically the whole Visuddhimāga commentaries, the whole Abhidharma to blame for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was a complete invention when they tried to popularize Buddhism for masses.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I told you, I think it was a buddhagosa who said, the the Visuddhimāga compiler, who said he hopes that his work will inspire people, whereby even common householders will speak about meditation on a daily basis, because it's a, you know...
[SPEAKER_00]: It became quite associated with the whole national pride, religion, the whole idea of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so it's no wonder that virtue had to suffer on account of it, the threshold of virtue, because that's one thing that that your average householder doesn't want to hear, doesn't want to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you lower that and present some... some more instantaneously gratifying yogic, tantric, hypnotic meditation techniques, then you would get probably quite a few followers in that regard.
[SPEAKER_00]: And ever since, even the whole, like, the... the Thai tradition and Boran Kamathan and the Thai forest meditation, you look at the history of it, it just came exactly from these abidamic views mixed with Tibetan and Chinese tantra,
[SPEAKER_00]: And in sort of visualization practices and stuff, and again...
[SPEAKER_00]: Intention for popularizing... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Came from the same source.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then even people with... And see why that's so dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even people who would have committed for right reasons to the practice, if that's where they arrived at, thinking that's what the Buddha actually taught, they wouldn't look further, and they'll be doing this nonsense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of doing the right thing, they were perfectly capable of doing, if they were told.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole... and same in Burma, the whole vipassana movement was told by that minister to the teacher of Mahāsī, like king's minister or something, because, again, he was like... he was very bound with their... with the Buddhist identity, colonial times, the pressures and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he was like, let's find the sutta that can serve as a basis, and then created these technique practices, which, by the way, are quite helpful management.
[SPEAKER_00]: Management techniques, like any other sort of practices, you might do to, like, you know, relieve the stress.
[SPEAKER_00]: But confusing that, for the Buddhist practice, it's pretty much confusing, basically, treating of a random symptom for the illness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when the symptom disappears, you think you're cured now, while actually your illness is deteriorating.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's the most perilous thing to do, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You read the suttas, the instruction to lay people, five precepts, eight precepts when you can, more often better, great.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, fulfill your other duties, but then at the same time reflect, reflect on the nature of enlightenment, reflect on the Buddha, the dhamma, the saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, it's always presented in that way, you know, through the oral transmission.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lots of details were lost, but you could extrapolate from that and see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, what is... what is... what would be the qualities, the properties of an enlightened mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it would be, obviously, disgust with sensuality, freedom from any... any physical cravings, freedom from conceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, okay, so all of these contexts, all of these ideas, think about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sit down for an hour, and instead of watching your belly rising up and down, think about the property of being free from conceit, and try and apply it.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the basis of your whatever limited virtue, limited sense restraint, still work in the same direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, the path does not magically become different just because you can't do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still the same practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pick up any other quality, same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Different times, different reflections, but invest time in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then try to apply it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you end up in situations that provoke your conceit, provoke your lust, provoke your anger, ah, that's the training now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tame the animal in regard to this, within my compromised environment, for which I have taken up responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even... that's something like... and that's why it's... you realize, like, all you can do is say these things, basically, to people, because
[SPEAKER_00]: At least one in hundred, when they hear it, they will be able to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the reason they were able to do it is because they actually heard it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were told.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't have an excuse to say, well, I was never told.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's kind of like the whole direction of what people like to think the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not incidental.
[SPEAKER_00]: That kind of... it does go with the general flow of nature, kind of preferences and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It kind of just tailors to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if, as I said, even if people were maybe misled, somebody told you this is the practice, unenlightened mind will quite happily leap onto that and proliferate further, and defend it, and so on, and not question it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, you might have been misled, but if you would have heard the other alternative, like this, and still irrationally chose this without any questioning, well, now that's your own doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you can do is keep saying it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because some people, at least when they hear it, well, they can't just go back to what they were doing before without asking certain questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you start asking them, you'll see how quickly the whole view will dissolve and how much it doesn't add up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the suttas are completely unambiguous about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the Buddha talked to lay people, when he was telling how to look after the wives, or kings how to rule, it was nothing to do with freedom from nibbāna, noble little path, and the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, freedom from from saṃsāra, nibbāna, and the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was for the heavenly rebirths, for the better life here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was because they clearly didn't want to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he would not have wasted the practice instruction that would have been misunderstood and misconstrued to somebody not even willing to hear it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when those lay people did, were instructed, it was exactly on the same basis as the monks were.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, there's the... keep the five precepts, you'll go to heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll enjoy sensual pleasures there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then there's the danger of those sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see, there's absolutely nothing wrong with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: That becomes a seriously mistaken and perilous position when, for whatever reason, that became understood as the practice of the dhamma as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's just delusional, as I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's the idea that the virtue is not... even the five precepts is not important, but the meditation is the core.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is even worse, because... Well, yeah, it's completely upside down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even if you keep the five precepts and you're aiming for the heavens, still you are in a way practicing the good path.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're not drifting away, too far away from the starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not practicing the path.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as I said before, by keeping the five precepts, which is, what I said, the bare minimum, you're at least, as I said, not too far off.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you do take the eight precepts, or start to practice sense restraint, or reflect on these right, correct contexts, and so on, you are actually close to where things would be starting.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're not even keeping the five precepts, and just doing some meditation, or occasionally keeping the precepts when you're on the retreat,
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, you can do whatever you want to manage your suffering and it's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's really no problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is when all those absolutely worldly misguided, in terms of the dhamma, managements are seen as the practice of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the worst thing you can do, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's even worse than somebody who is making no effort to practice, but at least is not obscuring what the practice actually is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you relegate virtue as being unimportant, that meditation insight, meditation experiences, as being the core, then, if you're a monk, or a layperson, it means, you know, what's the point of being monastic?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in a way, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then anybody, if the practice, everybody has access to the practice through meditation technique, everything else is secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, it's obviously, it's like the mainstream view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most people do it and most people say, well, but I find it helpful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody doubts that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody denies that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you need to really start looking into where the whole thing came from, because you're not going to find it in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: And whenever people don't say, oh, it comes from this sutta, it's always quite a... quite a leap to make those connections.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then people would sometimes just... just accept it, that it came from the suttas, because it was presented... the suttas were presented to them through these meditation techniques, and they haven't really looked into them and studied them for themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there were... there were books written on the whole origins of the, like, modern jhāna views and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe we can even link them, like a couple of... like full-on scholastic books, not just somebody expressing their view, like I'm doing now, and then quote the suttas, which, as I said, are fairly generic, people can interpret them whichever way they want.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, this was like a like a scholarly research on the basis of other research, of other research, full-on, like investigative work,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's just... there's no doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even people that practice the Buddhaghosa jhāna method and whatnot, that had nothing to do with the Buddhist jhānas, actually, even those scholars know that that didn't come from the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just accept and like and think Buddhaghosa knew what he was talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is absolutely no disagreement that that has come, like, 10 centuries later, 6, 11.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by that time, there was a lot, already like three centuries after the Buddha passed away, it was already, you know, by the time those saṅgha councils were coming, it was already different, different takes, yogic influences and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just to show you that, okay, you can do whatever you want, but if you want to claim it to be the dhamma and the practice for recruiting of the suffering and so on,
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to go back to the suttas, that, as I said, there is quite a wide consensus, the early texts, what they were, and really study them on their own merit, not like interpret them through your own, as I said, you know, breath, massage, tantric technique, and try to read into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, just look what it says, forget what you know, and what's the first thing that comes to your mind when you read an ānāpānasati sutta?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the first thing that comes to my mind is it wasn't taught to householders.
[SPEAKER_00]: The second thing that comes to my mind, it was taught to people with the right view, or with at least fully established virtue, sense restraint, like beyond any doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, you want to get in these other subsequent technicalities of jhāna, of ānāpānasati steps?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you gotta meet these technicalities first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is my life approximating that of a fully established in virtue, celibacy, sense restraint?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereby, I could say, well, it does apply to me, or no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you could say, oh, well, my teacher told me it doesn't have to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, we're not talking about your teacher.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're talking about the early Buddhist texts, the suttas, that are, as I said, widely agreed.
[SPEAKER_00]: OK, this is the closest to what the Buddha actually taught.
[SPEAKER_00]: And most likely, it was from the historical figure that did teach these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do those texts allow you to be a householder with the occasional five precepts, doing higher satipaṭṭhānas and ānāpānasati and four jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not a chance, by any stretch.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you could say, okay, I don't like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I do prefer my my lay jhāna teacher and I'll follow him.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you were told, and there is plenty of evidence to even prove that point, scholastic investigative works and stuff, that those are two different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I would see sometimes people go, oh no, there's the Buddha jhāna, and then there's this jhāna, this Ajahn's jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, no, there is jhāna, full stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no 16 types of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the subsequent jhānas are the ones that fail to understand or attain the Buddha's jhāna, the jhāna from the early texts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you wouldn't come up with your own practice of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's simply not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if the choice is clear, as I said before in other talks, you might even surprise yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think now, maybe you think, oh, it's just too much to do all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And once you're clear, once you calm down in your initial shock, because, you know, for 20 years you've been doing it this way, you might surprise yourself and realize, actually, I am kind of doing it like this, rightly now.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have, actually, a problem with the sense of strain as much as I thought I did.
[SPEAKER_00]: I could even do it more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Occasionally, I take on the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me take it on for longer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me now improve, like, the the restraint and the practice in regard to the the speech, the action revolving on speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, let me now, like Nanda Mata, purify thoughts in their manifestation, without relying on any management techniques.
[SPEAKER_00]: As they arise, I see through them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, she was a laywoman, with probably lots of duties and stuff and pressures, and she did all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, if, as a householder, you can become an anāgāmī, that's a pretty good deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, the practice is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's another thing, because, like, okay, so, could you become an anāgāmī, somebody who is fully, utterly, completely destroyed, the five lower fetters, it's above sensuality or real will, while practicing sexual activity?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, put everything, put all the text aside, all the teachings, just use clear reason, just pure logic, straightforward reflection, and see, can you do this and get this as a result of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: And see if that's just wishful thinking and a complete kind of, as I said, misled belief.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: By any stretch, if you just stop and think about it, you realize, no, of course, if I want to be beyond sensuality, I have to start emulating that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have to start not giving in to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a heroin addict, through shooting up drugs, genuinely believes, if he were to genuinely believe, that he will go beyond his addiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through feeding it every single day, he will go beyond it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't even need to become a heroin addict to realize that that's not how sensuality works.
[SPEAKER_00]: And somehow, you do have views of, I can just keep the five precepts the best I can, and practice for anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_01]: The destruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I find this secret pleasure hidden in the jhāna, that will then make me abandon the whole sensuality, never look back again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, again, you look at the actual suttas, and it's a very different picture painted there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't get the pleasure of renunciation by not... By not renouncing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in a way, it's actually like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm just imagining, like, if I were... if I were a householder and somebody tells me this, it's like, well, actually, that's kind of better.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to be relying on the magic of techniques and attainments.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had a special experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'd say, what does it mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: And stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then depend on someone else's word.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep the five precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep the eight when you can, do it as often as you can, moderate your engagement and compromise of sensuality and other things, and then you have plenty of opportunities for practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: People will be provoking you to say stuff, to think stuff, and you realize every single day you're served on a plate things that can directly lead to improvement of your citta or defilement of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you gotta do the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, yeah, actually, it's quite reasonable.
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody takes on that kind of work, even if it's five, occasional eight, five, occasional eight, but does all of this, does not mask or manage through techniques and mystical experiences and hypnotic trances, there's a good chance you could get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or at least, be like on the level of a dhamma nusāri and then get the right view at the moment of death or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind will be very clean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the mind... the mind is actually being worked properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: As opposed to just hypnotized, distracted, enticed with more sensuality to look away from this sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're taking it on rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, you're not going to be an arahant, but being a sotāpanna, it's, you know, as the Buddha said himself,
[SPEAKER_00]: In those suttas, it's worth being, what is it, like, stuck by a hundred spears every day for a hundred years.
[SPEAKER_00]: If at the end of that you were to get the sotāpārthi, it would be worth going through that pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nothing's stopping you, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing's stopping anyone, except their wrong views and mistaken, misplaced emphasis on what really the practice is and what's important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because although that's difficult and it's painful, a wise person would see that this pain is worth...
[SPEAKER_01]: This pain is the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, is the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because look at the results would be clarity of mind, steadiness of heart, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as a lay person, if you are still attached to your family and concerned with your children, your wife, wouldn't it be best if you had a clean mind, clean behavior?
[SPEAKER_00]: A non-clouded perspective in regard to what's best for them?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would that not inspire your own family?
[SPEAKER_01]: Wouldn't you be teaching your children the right way to live?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're beyond their will, beyond sensual...
[SPEAKER_01]: Isn't that the best thing that you should be doing for your family?
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's also good in other ways, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: I usually don't talk about that, because generally it's for like a wide audience, but the Buddha said himself, offering, feeding, helping a virtuous person will be like immeasurable merit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Offering, feeding, helping, sotāpāna, even more, sakadāgāmī, even more, anāgāmī, even more, arahant...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you yourself are actually the one with developed citta, as a householder, developed citta, developed virtue, on the way for the right view, dhammanusāri, sadhanusāri, committing to it rightly, anything good your wife, kids, friends do to you,
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like you are practicing for the benefit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Animals, they do something good for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are one with a purified citta, they're gonna reap manifold benefit from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were not,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's probably not gonna last for long.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's beneficial one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're becoming... And that's what I mean, like, and all this is in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: You really see, like, actually, that is perfectly doable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yes, many people would have valid reasons, you know, already have, you know, a growing family or people that depend on them, you know, maybe not as much as back in the day, in India,
[SPEAKER_00]: When you leave your family means, okay, they're done.
[SPEAKER_00]: But still, there is degree of responsibility and involvement and they can't just now...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too late, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too late to just give this up and become a monk because all of this...
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's like, okay, but it's not too late to internally start walking in the right direction on the basis of their compromised environment, take on that pain of untamed citta being faced correctly, tame it through virtue, five precepts,
[SPEAKER_00]: They keep you not drifting away from the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eight precepts that align you more with the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right reflections.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the reflections on your own family.
[SPEAKER_00]: See?
[SPEAKER_00]: You are... your children are your bond.
[SPEAKER_00]: What happens to bonds?
[SPEAKER_00]: What happens to those who are bonded?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, make your meditation around that every other day.
[SPEAKER_00]: One day, think about the virtue, the value of enlightenment, the value of immovable citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Another day, think about the petals of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Engage with sensuality when you have to, as I said, in a moderate way, but that still doesn't exempt you from thinking how bad it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about the danger of the bond.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about your children dying before you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would your mind remain immoved like Nanda Mata's did?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, it wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I gotta work towards that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't need to abandon children in order to do their work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's no excuse to not do the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's my point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you say, I can't become a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, still have to do the same work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I can't become celibate because I have duty towards wife.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Still think those same themes, contexts, and contemplations.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will keep you in check, but it's going to be unpleasant, because obviously you're in them and thinking them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, but that is your training there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you abandon that and become a monk, as in that environment and become a monk, you're going to have different types of
[SPEAKER_00]: Unpleasantness to think about.
[SPEAKER_00]: But one way or the other, it has to come, because we all start with an untamed citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: We all start with a wild animal that does need to be reined in, and then fed these perceptions, as the Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kept in front of it, until it sees for itself.